Finding aid for Library (University of Michigan) Clipping file, ca. 1920-1980
Bentley Historical Library
Library (University of Michigan) Clipping file
circa 1920-1980
1920/1970s
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Library.
87237 Bimu C416 2
76.5 linear feet
The Library Clipping File was a vertical file maintained by the University of Michigan Library Reference Department roughly from the early 1920s to the early 1980s. It largely consists of newspaper clippings on numerous topics relating to the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, and the State of Michigan, but includes some press releases, pamphlets, and printed ephemera as well.
The collection was transferred by the University of Michigan Library (Donor No. 1278 ) in 1983. An additional accession was received in 2004.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
This collection represents the clipping file as maintained by the Reference Department of the University of Michigan Library. The file was begun around 1920. Compilation of newspaper clippings largely ended by the mid 1970s, although some items date from the early 1980s. The collection consists of Four series of clipping files: University of Michigan, University of Micahign Faculty, Ann Arbor, and the State of Michigan. The clipping file is a useful starting point for information on particular events, individuals, issues, organizations, and subjects. In some instances the clippings supplement material held in the archives and provide detailed background on a variety of subjects as presented by local newspapers. Clippings in the University of Michigan series were tipped into folder often using mounting hinges, thus maintaining a rough chronology within folders. Clippings in the Ann Arbor and State of Michigan series are loose, although some articles have been clipped together with a scrap of paper noting specific chronological periods.
The Ann Arbor series and the State of Michigan series were transferred to the Bentley Library in 2004. These two series include a few items from the late 1970s and early 1980s, and retain scattered pamphlets and other non-newspaper printed material. The folder headings for the two series represent headings used by the Library, with limited cross references added by Bentley staff. However, as in the University of Michigan series, there is significant overlap in the file names for the Ann Arbor and State of Michigan series This is most notable in the State of Michigan series, which includes a large run of subjects under the heading of "Michigan -- ." Researchers looking for Michigan topics in this series should check both under the "Michigan" hierarchy and under the topic name in the overall alphabetical list.
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Schools -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan -- History -- 20th century.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1921-1930.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1931-1940.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1941-1950.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1951-1960.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1961-1970.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1971-1980.
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series (57.0 linear feet, 1920s-1970s) comprises the first accession to the collection. It contains clippings and press releases relating tot he university, its faculty, staff, students, and alumni. Both the headings and cross references in the inventory for this series come from the Library file, with Bentley box numbers marked on the list. As maintained by the University of Michigan Library, the file included many series of reports and university publications that were catalogued separately within the Bentley Historical Library. Those publications were removed from this series before the original accession. The extensive cross references help provide an index of sorts to broad campus topics as well as more detailed information on campus visitors, one-time events, and various traditions and rites. The clippings are particularly rich in information on student clubs, organizations, and fraternities and sororities. Clippings on campus buildings, monuments and statuary are present along with material on scientific expeditions, academic departments, international students, and sports.
  - A
    - For general data not proper to any one folder see MiU-University Relations Service
    - ADA.
      (see: MiU-Political Clubs-Americans for Democratic Action)
    - AID contract program (U.S. Agency for International Development) seer MiU-Engineering, College of, or other dept. involved
    - A.I.M.
      (see: MiU-Association for Independent Men MiU-APA. see: MiU-Dramatics-Professional Theater Program)
    - A Hop (Sponsored by Assembly)
      (see: MiU-Assembly (From 1948-52 jointly by Assembly and AIM See: MiU-Independents)
    - Abstracts of Hospital Management.
      (see: MiU-Bureau of Hospital Administration.)
    - Academic Counselor Service.
      (see: MiU-Advisors)
    - Academic Freedom (Box 1)
      (Academic Freedom Week and other groups sponsored by the Student Government. see also: MiU-Free Speech; MiU-Political Clubs; MiU-Radicals; Academic Freedom (general file))
    - Academic Year Institutes 1858-9 (Sponsored by the Mathematic and other sciences departments. Head-.Dr. Miller, Astronomy)
      (see: Science)
    - Accidents
      (see: Student Accidents (For others see also Employees; vacuity))
    - Accounting.
      (see: Business Administration, School of)
    - Accreditation of Schools.
      (see: Bureau of School Services)
    - Acoustics and Seismics Laboratory (until known as Fluid and Solid Mechanics Lab.), September 1961
      (see: Institute of Science and Technology)
    - Activism.
      (Includes Vietnam protest "Teach-in", 1965 and similar protests. ROTC protest. see also: Housing (for rent strikes); Race Problems; ROTC; Cooperative Stores (for bookstore controversy)
      - 1965 (Box 1)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Activities Center.
      (see: University Activities Center)
    - Activities Building.
      (see: Student Activities Center)
    - Actuarial Science (Insurance).
      (see: Mathematics, Dept. of)
    - Adelphi.
      (see: Societies-Debating and Oratorical)
    - Administration--Pamphlets-Clippings
      (see also: Faculty-(Name); Student-Faculty-Administration Relations)
      - 1922-1932 (Box 1)
      - 1933-1944 (Box 1)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 1)
      - 1947-1950 (Box 1)
      - 1950-1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Administration Building.
      (see: Building Program Admissions. see: Entrance Requirements; Enrollment.)
    - Adult Education, Division of. Wayne State University-University of Michigan (a joint program).
      (see: Extension-Adult Education Program)
    - Adult Education Institute.
    - Advance, see Student Publications-Literary
    - Advance Placement English Conference.
      (see: Ann Arbor-Schools (general file))
    - Advertising
      (see: Business Administration, School of (also some data in Journalism))
    - Advisors (Chiefly for the Lit. School). See also Engineering, College of and other schools) For Freshman orientation (Box 1)
      (see: Freshmen; Women's League; Union.)
    - "Aequanimitas" University Medical School Yearbook 1957.
      (see: Medical School)
    - Aero Branch of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers. Merged with Inst. of Aero Sciences; 1936.
      (see: Societies-Aero)
    - Aerospace Engineering Dept. of
      (see: Engineering, College of-Aeronautical and Astronautical (Name changed to Dept. of Aerospace Engineering, June 18, 1965)
    - Affirmative Action Program, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - African Union.
      (see: Foreign Students-Societies-Africa and Near East)
    - Afro-American Studies.
      (see: Black Studies; Race Relations; Black people-Education (general file))
    - Age of Opportunity Conference.
      (see: Institute for Human Adjustment-Gerontology Division of)
    - Aging.
      (see: Institute for Human Adjustment-Gerontology, Division, of; Ann Arbor-Old Age (Senior Citizens Guild); Old Age-Michigan)
    - Air Force Association
      (see: Veterans-Societies)
    - Air Force Reserve Officers Training Corps. (Box 1)
      (see: Air Science, Dept. of)
    - Air Science, Dept. of
      (see also: ROTC (joint actions); World War II-Army and Naval Educ. prig.; Societies-Aeronautical; Societies-Military; Engineering, College of-Aero (uses these facilities); Naval Science, Dept. of (for naval aviation))
    - Albeneri Trio.
      (see: Chamber Music)
    - Aleutians and Alaska Expeditions. Led by Dr. Bank
      (see: Expeditions-Pacific,)
    - John Alexander Surgical Society.
      (see: Societies-Medical School)
    - Alice's Restaurant.
      (see: Dormitories (Gen.) Located in Alice Lloyd Hall, 1968-)
    - All Nations Club. Brief international club sponsored by the International Center. See also Foreign Students-Societies folders for other clubs.
      (see: Foreign Students-International Center)
    - Alpha Alpha Gamma
      (see: Societies-Architecture and Art)
    - Alpha Chi Sigma (National Prof. Chemical Frat.)
      (See: Societies-Chemistry Alpha Delta Chi.; Societies-Architecture and Art)
    - Alpha Epsilon Iota. Women's Medical Sorority.
    - Alpha Epsilon Mu. National Honorary Fraternity.
      (see: Societies-Music)
    - Alpha Gamma Sigma. Campus Campfire Girls Organization.
      (see: Societies-Women Alpha Kappa Delta. Sociology Honor Society. see: Sociology, Dept. of)
    - Alpha Kappa Kappa. Medical Fraternity.
      (see: Societies-Medical School Alpha Kappa Psi. (Prof. of Bus. Ad. Frat.) see: Societies-Bus. Ad. Alpha Lambda Delta. see: Societies-Alpha Lambda Delta)
    - Alpha Nu.
    - Alpha Omega Alpha. Medical Honor Society.
      (see: Societies-Medical School Alpha Phi Omega. see: Societies-Alpha Phi Omega)
    - Alpha Pi Mu.
      (see: Societies-Engineering)
    - Alpha Rho Chi.
    - Alpha Tau Sigma (Eng. Journalism Honorary).
    - Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam, Conference on (September 1965).
      (see: Activism)
    - Alumnae Council (Box 1)
      (Projects include: Funds for League Bldg.; C.N. Kellog Professorship; remodeling Henderson House; Alice Crocker Lloyd and Lucy Elliot Fellowships; scholarships; Children's Theater (1948-) see also: League Building; Alumni Association)
    - Alumnae Hall.
      (see: Co-operative Rooming and Boarding Projects)
    - Alumni
      - General
        - Pamphlets (Box 1)
        - Clippings
          - 1921-1932 (Box 1)
          - 1933-1944 (Box 1)
          - 1945- (Box 1)
      - Alphabetical
        - A (Box 1)
        - Ba-Bl (Box 1)
        - Bo-By (Box 1)
        - Ca-Cl (Box 1)
        - Co-Cu (Box 1)
        - Da-De (Box 1)
        - Di-Dy (Box 1)
        - F (Box 2)
        - G (Box 2)
        - Ha-Hi (Box 2)
        - Ho-J (Box 2)
        - K (Box 2)
        - L (Box 2)
        - M-Mn (Box 2)
        - Mo-O (Box 2)
        - P-Q (Box 2)
        - R (Box 2)
        - Sa-Sh (Box 2)
        - Si-Ste (Box 2)
        - Sti-Sz (Box 2)
        - T (Box 2)
        - U-Wa (Box 2)
        - We-Z (Box 2)
    - Alumni.
      (See also: Homecoming; Publications; Relations; Reunions; University of Michigan Club (AA); Alumni Asociation-10 Year Program; Finances-Alumni Aid; Alumni Memorial Hall; Alumnae Council, Scholarships)
    - Alumni-Astronauts (Box 2)
    - Alumni-(W.W.) Cook.
      (see: Law School-W.W. Cook Foundation)
    - Alumni-Astronauts
    - Alumni -- Ford, Gerald (Box 2)
    - Alumni-Alumni-Homecoming
      - 1930-1947 (Box 2)
      - 1948-1955 (Box 2)
      - 1956- (Box 2)
    - Alumni-Miller, Arthur. (Box 2)
      (see also: Hopwood Awards; Dramatics (Prod. of his plays))
    - Alumni-Publications. (Box 2)
      (see also: Publications; Michigan Alumnus; Michigan Quarterly Review. (Alumnus))
    - Alumni-Relations (Box 2)
    - Alumni-Reunions. (Box 2)
      (see also: Reunions of various schools and colleges, e.g., Medical, etc.)
    - Alumni-Scholarships.
      (see: Alumni (general); Alumnae Council; Scholarships; Fellowships)
    - Alumni-University of Michigan Club (AA) (Box 2)
    - Alumni Advisory Council.
      (see: Alumni Relations)
    - Alumni Association. see also: Alumni Association-10 Year Program; Alumni University
      - 1923-1949 (Box 2)
      - 1950- (Box 2)
    - Alumni Association-10 Year Program (Box 2)
    - Alumni Band.
      (see: Bands-Marching Band)
    - Alumni Catalog Office.
      (see: Alumni-Relations)
    - Alumni Fund.
      (see: Finances-Alumni Aid)
    - Alumni Memorial Hall and Art Collection.
      (see: Museum of Art)
    - Alumni Reading Lists.
      (see: Library-Extension)
    - Alumni University.-Lectures and Texts
    - 1927-1936 (Box 2)
    - 1938- (Box 2)
    - American Association of University Professors.
      (see: Societies-Faculty)
    - American Association of University Women. (Represented on campus by the Alumnae Council.)
      (see: Alumnae Council)
    - "American Brother" Program. (Part of the Union International Committee..
      (see: Union-Activities)
    - American-Canadian Relations.
      (see: Summer Session-Campus Events (19149-50) American Chemical Society. see: Societies-Chemistry)
    - American Culture, Dept. of (Box 3)
    - American Culture and Institutions, Graduate Program in (19140) (Box 3)
    - American Foundrymen's Association.
    - American Institute of Architecture.
      (see: Societies-Architecture and Art American Institute of Chemical Engineers. see: Societies-Chemistry)
    - American Institute of Architecture
      (see: Societies -- Architecture and Art)
    - American Institute of Aeronautics and Engineering
    - American Institute of Electrical Engineers
    - American Institute of Mining and Metallurgical Engineers
    - American Journal of Comparative Law.
      (see: Law School-Publications)
    - American Judicature Society. (Independent organization which resided at the Law School until 19514).
      (see: Law School)
    - American Legion.
    - American Medical Association (Student Branch).
    - American Nuclear Society.
      (see: Phoenix Project-Institutes and ...)
    - American Oriental Society.
      (see: Far Eastern Studies)
    - American Pharmaceutical Association.
      (see: Pharmacy, College of)
    - American Policy in the War Crisis.
      (see: Slimmer Session-Campus Events (1940))
    - American Rocket Society.
      (see: Societies-Aeronautical)
    - American Society for Public Administration.
      (see: Societies-Business Administration)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers.
    - American Society of Engineering Education.
    - American Society of Tool Engineers.
    - American Society of Women Engineers.
    - American Student Union
      - National Organization; for campus club.
        (see: Political Clubs-Progressive Club.)
      - 1947
        (became Student League for Industrial Democracy; for campus club. see: Political Clubs-Round Table Club,)
      - 19486 became Young People's Socialist League
      - Returned to title--Student League for Industrial Democracy., 1951
    - American Youth for Democracy.
      (see: Political Clubs-Michigan Youth for Democratic Action)
    - Americans Committed to World Responsibility.
      (see: Political Clubs-International Relations)
    - Americans for Democratic Action (ADA).
      (see: Political Clubs-Americans for Democratic Action)
    - America's Town Meeting of the Air.
      (see: Michigan Forum)
    - Angell, President, James B. (Box 3)
    - Angell Hall. For astronomy observatory. (Box 3)
      (see: Observatory)
    - Angell Hall Playhouse.
      (see: Radio)
    - Angell (Robert C.) Reports (192/1-29). Reports made to the regents on the cultural life and living conditions of the students at the U. of M. (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor Independent Women.
      (see: Societies-Independents)
    - Ann Arbor Playmakers. Formerly called DoDos.
      (see: Dramatics-Faculty and Town Groups)
    - Ann Arbor Swim Club.
      (see: Swimming and Aquatic Sports-Women)
    - Annuities, etc. (Box 3)
      (Includes Annuitants Association. For Blue Cross. see: Hospitalization Plans)
    - Anthropology Club.
      (see: Anthropology, Dept. of)
    - Anthropology, Dept. of.
      (see also: Kelsey Museum of Archaeology; Museums)
      - 1920-1955 (Box 3)
      - 1956- (Box 3)
    - Antioch of Psidia.
      (see: Near Eastern Studies-Expeditions)
    - Apostles.
    - Apothecaries Club.
    - Applied Botany Laboratory.
      (see: Botany, Dept. of)
    - Appointment Bureau.
      (see: Bureau of Appointments and Occupation Information Appropriations. see: Finances)
    - Arab Club.
    - Arab Conference.
      (see: Near Eastern Studies, Dept. of)
    - Arboretum.
    - "Arch" Engineering Newspaper.
      (see: Engineering, College of-Technic and Arch)
    - Archaeology.
      (see: Anthropology, Dept. of; Kelsey Museum of)
    - Archaeology, Classical.
      (see: Classical Studies, Dept. of)
    - Archery (Box 3)
    - .Architectural Society.
    - Architecture and Design, College of (Until 1931-Architectural Dept.)
      (see also: Societies-Architecture and Art; Landscape Architecture, Dept. of)
      - 1923-1928 (Box 3)
      - 1929-1932 (Box 3)
      - 1933-1947 (Box 3)
      - 1948-1953 (Box 3)
      - 1954-1961 (Box 3)
    - Architecture and Urban Planning, College, 1974- (Box 3)
    - Archives.
      (see: History-Michigan Historical Collections)
    - Area Programs.
      (see: American Culture, Dept. of; Far Eastern Studies, rept. of; Near Eastern Studies, Dept. of; Slavic Language and Literature, Dept. of (Russian Studies))
    - Argonne Universities Association, Inc. (A.U.A.).
      (see: Joint Programs (General) For material on research at Argonne labs., see: research)
    - Ark (Box 3)
    - Armed Forces.
      (see: Card for Military Affairs, Office of)
    - Armed Forces Day.
      (see: Ann Arbor-Defense)
    - Arms Control and Disarmament, Faculty Seminar on.
      (see: Center for Research on Conflict Resolution)
    - Arms Control and Peace Research, Institute for.
      (see: Peace Movements. Will publish Journal of Arms Control)
    - Arms Control Symposium, International.
      (see: Peace Movements)
    - Army Ordnance Association.
      (see: Societies-Military)
    - Arnold Air Society.
    - Arson Detection and Investigation Seminars.
      (see: Extension-Firemanship Training)
    - Art.
      (see: Fine Arts, Dept. of; Architecture and Design, College of; Societies-Architecture and Art; Art, Student; Graduate School, Exhibit in Building; Extension-Audio-Visual Education Center; Art Print Loan Collection; Museum of Art; Ann Arbor-Art)
    - Art, School of, 1974- (Box 3)
    - Art; Student. Independent work done by students for sale or exhibit (other than in Rackham).
      (see also: Graduate School-Exhibits in Building; Fine Arts, Dept. of; Architecture and Design, College of; Societies-Architecture and Art)
    - Art Cinema League.
      (see: Moving Pictures-Art Cinema League)
    - Art History Dept.
      (see: Fine Arts, Dept. of)
    - Art Masterwork Collection.
      (see: Extension-Audio-Visual Center)
    - Art Print Loan Collection (Box 3)
    - Art Student Guild.
      (see: Art, Student)
    - Arts Chorale. Literary College Glee Club.
      (see: Glee Clubs-Extra-Curricular Groups)
    - Asia and Asian Civilization.
    - Asian Association.
      (see: Foreign Students-Societies-Asia)
    - Asian Cultures and the Modern American. Summer Session Lecture Series, 1957. .see: Summer Session-Campus Events
    - Asian Tour (1958).
      (see: Student Government (1957- ))
    - Assembly. Independent Women's Organization.
      (In 1966 merged with Inter-House Council to form Inter-House Assembly (i.e., Assembly Association merged)) see also: Independents (for Joint action with men); Societies-Circle)
    - Assessors' Training Institute.
      (see: Extension-Institutes Associated Women Students. see: Women's League)
    - Association for Independent Men (AIM)., 1948-1952 (Box 3)
      (Organized the Inter-Dorm council. Replaced by Dorms (men)-Inter-House Council.)
    - Association for Social Action (formerly SAIL; .Student's Association for International Living).
      (see: Race Problems)
    - Association of Governing Boards and Presidents of the State Universities and Colleges in Mich.
      (see: Education-Michigan (general file))
    - Association of Religious Counselors (ARC). Co-ordinates the professional and voluntary religious advisors.
      (see: Religious Affairs, Office of)
    - Association of University of Michigan Scientists
      (see: Societies-Association of U. of M. Scientists)
    - Astronauts.
      (see: Alumni-Astronauts)
    - Astronomy, Dept. of.
    - Athletic Medicine Program.
    - Athletics (list of folders on individual sports)
      (For items not listed heresee: Athletics-Intramural; Athletics-Intramural-Women. (Unless a separate folder is specified women are included in the folder listed.))
      Archery
      Baseball
      Baseball and Softball-Women
      Basketball
      Basketball-Women
      Dance
      Fencing
      Field Hockey
      Football
      Football-"All American" teams
      Football-Tickets
      Golf
      Golf-Women
      Gymnastics
      Hockey and Skating
      Societies-Outing
      Riding
      Rifle teams
      Sailing
      Skiing
      Swimming and Aquatic Sports
      Swimming and Aquatic Sports-Women
      Tennis; Track
      Wrestling and Boxing
    - Athletics -- Clippings and Pamphlets
      (Includes general information on-inter-collegiate awards, records, Michigan Night programs by alumni, housing of visitors, scholarships and student aid for athletics, MSU-MU controversy, scandals and press comments on Mill athletics, etc.)
      - 1920-1945 (Box 3)
      - 1946- (Box 3)
    - Athletics
      (see also: Athletics-Administration: Athletics Conferences; Athletics-Ferry Field; Athletics-Intramural; Athletics-Intramural-Women; Athletics-"Pep"; Athletics --Stadium; Athletics-Women's; Athletic Association; Physical Education for men; Dept. of Physical Education for women;)
    - Athletics-Administration.
      (Includes the Athletic Association; Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics; general data on building program, revenue, coupon books, Eligibility Board, staff, etc. see also: Athletics (clippings) (pamphlets); Physical Ed. for Men, Dept. of (for staff))
      - 1920-1935 (Box 3)
      - 1935-1952 (Box 3)
      - 1953- (Box 3)
    - Athletics-Building Program.
      (see: Athletics-Administration for general data See also: Golf; Athletics-Ferry Field; Athletic-Stadium; Athletics-Intramural; Athletics-WAA)
    - Athletics-Conference. (Box 3)
      (Includes Western Conference, Big Ten, etc. see also: Athletics; Athletics-Administration for controversies)
    - Athletics-Ferry Field. (Box 3)
      (see also: Athletics-Intramural)
    - Athletics-Intramural.
      (Includes all minor sports groups even if independent clubs. Soccer; Handball; Speedball; Lacrosse; Bowling (see also: Union))
      - 1930-July 1932 (Box 3)
      - August 1932- (Box 3)
    - Athletics-Intramural-Women. (Box 3)
      (Includes all minor sports clubs: Bowling; Speedball; Badminton; Lacrosse; Soccer; Official's Club; Camp Counselor's Club)
    - Athletics-"Pep", 1938- (Box 4)
      (Includes cheering section, cheer leaders, Pep rallies, etc.)
    - Athletics-Societies. (Box 4)
      (Includes M Club, Wolverine Club, Physical Education Club for Women, Managers Club, Sigma Delta Psi, Phi Epsilon Kappa)
    - Athletics-Stadium (Box 4)